Guide to the Eula Davies Collection of Napoleonica 1838-2004 MS 002
Southern Connecticut State University, Publisher
Eula Davies Collection of Napoleonica1838-2004
MS 002
15? linear feet
Southern Connecticut State University
Davies, Eula
Collection contains statues, medals, stamps and prints of Napoleon.
Provenance
Gift of Eula Davies.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Davies was an alum of Southern Connecticut State University, class of 1948. She was a collector of Napoleonica and passed away in 2004.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is divided into two parts: Items 1-5, Statues, Medals and Stamps; and items 6-35, prints.
Arrangement
The itesm are grouped into 2 series:
Statues, Medals and Stamps
Prints
Access Points
Subject Names:
Davies, Eula.; Napoleon I, Emperor of the French, 1769-1821.
Subject Topics:
Napoleon I, Emperor of the French, 1769-1821 -- Portraits.; France -- History -- Consulate and First Empire, 1799-1815.; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815 -- Portraits.
Document Types:
Prints (visual works).; Busts.; Statues.; Postage stamps.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Statues, Medals and Stamps
  - White marble statue of standing Napoleon, 15" high., undated (Item 1)
  - Bronze statue of Napoleon standing on black marble base, 8 ½" high, sword broken., undated (Item 2)
  - Bronze-colored white metal busts of Napoleon I & Napoleon III, possibly book ends, about 5 ¼" high., undated (Item 3)
  - Frame with 7 Liberian stamps featuring Napoleon, as well as two small medals of the same., undated (Item 4)
  - Frame with 16 Liberian stamps featuring Napoleon., undated (Item 5)
- Prints
  - Two framed prints for exhibit Napoleon in English Caricature at the Huntington Library, California 1974/5. About 16" x 20"., ca.1974 (Item 6a & 6b.)
  - Framed print entitled Levée du siège de Mantoue. An incident in the campaign of 1796 during the French revolutionary wars. About 13" x 10 ½"., undated (Item 7)
  - Framed print entitled Le passage du Saint Bernard. Chromolithograph depicting the forcing of the St. Bernard Pass prior to the Battle of Marengo, 1800. About 9" x 11 ¾", undated (Item 8)
  - Framed print entitled Las Casas and His Son Writing the History of Napoleon under his Dictation. "Aquarelle made for the Century Co." "From the Aquarelle by F. De Myrbach." "Typogravure Boussard, Valadon & Co., Paris." Depiction of Emmanuel Las Cases taking dictation from Napoleon on St. Helena where he wrote Mémorial de Sainte-Hélène [1823]. Interesting example of aquatint process. Print has been damaged by poor mounting., undated (Item 9)
  - Framed photograph of section of larger painting. Inscription at bottom obscure, but "Musee de Versailles…….Ier a………..Gosse. X. Phot." About 7" x 4 5/8"., undated (Item 10)
  - Framed photograph of section of larger painting of defeated Napoleon. "Photogravure Goupil & Co." About 6 ½" x 4 ¾"., undated (Item 11)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon on green ground with wreath of olive branches superimposed by crown. In left corner "Frederic Masson de l'academie franciase," in center "Napoleon" while in lower right "Illustrations de F. Myrbach." Possibly the cover of a portfolio collection. About 8 ½" x 11"., undated (Item 12)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon, " Lith & Pub by N. Currier 2 Spruce St. NY" At this address from 1838 to 1856. Hand-colored lithograph. About 13" x 17 ¾"., ca.1838-1856 (Item 13)
  - Framed print of Napoleon and others, The Abdication, Fontainebleau, April 6, 1814:00:00 From the Painting of Etienne Prosper Berne-Bellecour, "typogravure Boussod, Valadon & Co., Paris." About 7 ¼" x 9 ¼"., undated (Item 14)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon, Napoleon in 1813 From the painting by Amable-Claude Pagnest…engraved by T. Johnson. About 7" x 9"., undated (Item 15)
  - Framed print of Napoleon and others, The Abdication, Fontainbleau, April 6, 1814 From the painting of Etienne Prosper Berne-Bellecour….typogravure Doussod, Valadon & Co., Paris. About 9 ¼" x 8 ¼"., undated (Item 16)
  - Framed print of Napoleon and others, The Surrender of Buonaparte on board the Bellerophon. "G. M. Brighty del [drawn]…….Pubd by T. Kinnersley June 1. 1816…..G. P. Palmer Sculp [engraved]." About 10" x 7 ½"., undated (Item 17)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon standing, camp in background. Napoleon Bonaparte. Quote: "Who born no King, .made Monarchs draw his car….Byron." "No. 64…..H. Dawe scupt.[engraved]" Aquatint? About 9 ¼" x 7 ¼"., undated (Item 18)
  - Small portrait of Napoleon, apparently cut out of a promotional brochure for a print of the Battle of Wagram (1809). About 2 ¾" x 5"., undated (Item 19)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon in oval cartouche, 4 ¾" x 6 5/8", below: NAPOLEON BONAPARTE LIEUTENANT Colonel Ier. BON DE LA CORSE en 1792 NAPOLEON Ier. EMPEREUR DES FRANCAIS 1804., undated (Item 20)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon in oval 6 3/8" apparently a photolithograph of a painting, possibly cut from a magazine., undated (Item 21)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon in oval 9 ½" apparently a photolithograph of a painting, possibly from a book., undated (Item 22)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon 4 7/16" x 6 3/8" apparently a photolithograph of a painting., undated (Item 23)
  - Framed portrait of Napoleon 7 ½" x 9 ¼" apparently a lithograph of an engraving, Napoleon Bonaparte Lieutenant-Colonel of the First Battalion of Corsica from the painting by H. E. F Philippoteaux., undated (Item 24)
  - Framed colored portrait of Napoleon standing in front of desk, tall case clock in background, 6" x 9 1/8". Photolithograph cut from some other source., undated (Item 25)
  - Framed colored portrait of Napoleon on deathbed with olive crown, 7 ½" x 9 ½"., undated (Item 26)
  - Framed colored portrait of Napoleon standing, church in background, 7 7/8" x 11 3/8". Photolithograph of painting, cut from some large work., undated (Item 27)
  - Framed colored (blue and gold) portrait of Napoleon on horseback 15 ½" x 23", NAPOLEON. And "Propriete de l'Editeur. (Dépose)," and "A Epinal, chez PELLERION, Imprimeur-Libraire.", undated (Item 28)
  - Large framed portrait of Napoleon, 17" x 21"., undated (Item 29)
  - Unmounted poster for world premier of opera Napoleon by Robert Beadell (1924-1995), 22" x 25 ½" in Kimball Hall, venue uncertain., undated (Item 30)
  - Framed color portrait of Napoleon, 8 ½" x 11 ¼"., undated (Item 31)
  - Framed colored acquaint, portrait of Napoleon in oval, Bonaparte Premier Consul de la Republique Francais below scene of military revue in the Place du Caroussel, "Revue du Quintidi a Paris, chez Xubev Editeur Rue 2 St. Lazare Chausseé de Aulin No. 88," ""Déposé a la Bibliotheque Nle le 1 of Messidor, Year X [1801]. At left: "Boilly Penxil," at center: "Duplessia Bevtaux aqua forti," at right "Levachez Sculpt.", undated (Item 32)
  - Framed engraving of retreat from Moscow, 1814. About 17 ¼ x 24" from the painting (1864) by Jean-Louise-Ernest Meissonier (1815-1891), engraved by Jules Jacquet, printed by A. Solomon, Paris. (Item 33)
  - Framed colored portrait of a young Napoleon 13 "x 17". Elaborate frame much damaged from move., undated (Item 34)
  - Pair of dismounted colored engravings about 10" x 9" entitled ON NE PASSE PAS and APRES VOUS SIRE concerning the life of Napoleon. "à Paris chez Desmaisons, rue Guenegaud. 14. Dauty Palais Royal Galerie de Namours." Both damaged by poor mounting adhesive., undated (Item 35a & 35b)